[SPEAKER_01]: What about mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, composure is a result of mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, composure is a result, can be a result, or rather, the right composure is the result of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Disenchantment, nibbida, disgust towards the world, towards the senses, sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the composure you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want some sort of contemporary concentration technique or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want composure based on dispassion, based on turning away from the desires towards the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness of death provides you with that, but as
[SPEAKER_02]: As it was the case in the suttas, it's a bit... well, you can push some people over the edge.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, the Buddha offered the alternative, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: the same thing, just in the form of mindfulness of breathing, just in the form of a less personal approach.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, in mindfulness of that, you begin,
[SPEAKER_02]: Thinking through your point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness of breathing, you take the breathing as a point of view, not yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you are breathing in like this, I'm breathing like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But basically, the fact that the Buddha offered it instead of maraṇasati means it's that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It pertains to that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you do mindfulness of breathing rightly, you are basically contemplating death rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're experiencing dispassion towards the world rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said to Āceta Sūta, he was teaching the Subha meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, it was Subha, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I was trying to basically... Subha and death, kind of, just discussed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, as I said, it comes to me and this body and I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if done rightly, the Buddha said, it's like, bear fruit in no time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Full dispassion right away.
[SPEAKER_02]: But,
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people might get a bit too much, and then they'll think, like, oh, I'm better off without this body, and then they'll be jumping off the cliffs and... and asking those other... that crazy man to kill them with a sword, and... and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was going to say this.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's... what's the end goal of the marathon, the training?
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that is basically rooted or springs from correct dispassion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you feel no desire towards the world, towards life.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, you don't feel any desire towards death either.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because death is the sort of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the notion of death requires, as a basis, the notion of life that you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's when people... when people are involved with the life, that's when they want death.
[SPEAKER_02]: When that life sort of doesn't go their way, or goes... or it's actually unpleasant, then they want death.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the same desire, they were wanting life, now they want the ending of life.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you feel dispassion towards that life, you feel dispassion towards... you don't care whether that life is there or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you don't care whether you're alive or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you cannot possibly be desiring death either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why would you be dispassionate towards life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you be ex-vijānta?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's... What?
[SPEAKER_01]: What way do you see, like, you watch the breath and you become dispassionate towards life, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: You see that the body's...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you mean, how will breath make you dispassionate towards life?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, understanding that your life can end at any next in-breath or out-breath without your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you actually have to take that idea
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to think about the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just be watching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be thinking about what is going on here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, I said millions of times before, I'm not talking about modern vipassana techniques, or Burmese, or whatnot, or even what people think mindfulness of breathing is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, not at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all nonsense.
[SPEAKER_02]: You read the suttas, and the Buddha's quite clear how you do the breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You breathe in like this, you breathe in like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, you're actively involving your volition in the way how you breathe while you're being mindful of that breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you do that steadily enough, it will reveal you that no amount of volition can cross that threshold after which the breath becomes in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, the life that is provided by the breath
[SPEAKER_02]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only control the manner of your breathing, but the way that your life depends upon your breath, that's completely inconceivable for you to control, to access, to have any input on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could just be breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always afraid that no amount of control that you're right now exerting here, breathing in slowly, breathing in relaxingly, breathing in like this, and breathing in like that, and breathing in pleasantly, no amount of that control can sort of obscure or prevent the clarity of the life can end the very next in-breath or out-breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just cannot cross into that
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how you also uproot the notion of self, the notion of me and mine in regard to your own volition, which is the hardest thing to do, because that's the closest to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That intention, that direction, the point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you see no amount... and you do that long enough, like mindfully, willingly, intentionally, yeah, you're leaving nothing out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever is there, you're seeing as dependent upon that which is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is basically that breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: The life aspect in that breath, that's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: The manner of your breathing, you can control.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that your life depends upon that breath, you cannot control.
[SPEAKER_02]: That bodily breath?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that very bodily breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the organs and air moving and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is... See, if I want my attention to breathe,
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I actually watch my intention to breathe, you say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you watch that by breathing, by being mindful of your breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, there's a tension to breathe.
Yeah.
In a particular way.
I can say I'm breathing in, calming the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result of that, what I see, coming at the same time, is my... is the body breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, tension is present there simultaneously with the body breathing in such manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how does the intention look?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I get confused whether am I now paying attention to the actual body breathing?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I paying attention?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter why you're paying attention, as long as you're including both things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your attention can be paying more attention to the bodily aspect or the I am breathing aspect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is it going?
[SPEAKER_02]: As long as both things are included and nothing is left out in regard to seeing that fundamental dependence upon that which is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Organs, oxygen present in the breath, whatever you want to call it, whatever you want to label it, whatever you want to designate it, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is that your intentional breathing and the fact that your life depends upon it, you can control only so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ultimately, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, you're just keeping it, keeping it active.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to give it a directive to remain mindful of your very volition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the moment you slip into a method or a technique, you're done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness cannot be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't mean that every next breath you have to do differently.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those are just listed, the ways you can be doing it while remaining mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, within that mindfulness of the general, kind of,
[SPEAKER_02]: Of the fact, of the general fact, that you're being undermined, basically, by the nature of your life's dependence upon breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot access that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be breathing as softly, smoothly, and as controlling as you can be, but the dependence, the phenomenon that your life depends upon it, upon the presence of that breath, that's something you cannot control.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's just there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if that changes, no amount of your breathing will keep you alive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Think of it like, you keep breathing normally, but suddenly there's no oxygen in your breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're breathing some, I don't know, carbon monoxide.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're still breathing, but you're not actually going to be alive for much longer, despite your same volition, same efforts and everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: But these external circumstances, external form that your life depends upon, has changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you cannot, you cannot have an input in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot breathe in in such a manner to, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Maintain your life, so to speak, despite the absence of oxygen in the air you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, the aspects upon which your life depends are out of your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, not knowing that clearly enough, the notion of control that you have, or rather, the notion of volition that we have, that we can exercise, induce the notion of ultimate control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you think you're breathing because you're alive, because your life is in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if you suddenly end up somewhere where there is no oxygen to breathe in, you thought that was an unfortunate incident or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact is that such things are possible means that your life is rooted outside of your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you are truly in your control, no incidents or accidents could happen to you of any kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, breath, obviously, is the most personal action you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why it's a good
[SPEAKER_02]: way to reveal this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, really, your whole life, like, you can be breathing and breathing, but... and, like, okay, forget about it, and also, let's say, you don't... you don't know any chemistry and stuff, so you don't think about oxygen or carbon monoxide or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just have the phenomenon, like... like mindfulness of the clear air passage in your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what your life depends on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if something obstructs it internally, your life's ending.
[SPEAKER_02]: Done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your heart stops pumping,
[SPEAKER_02]: No amount of breathing can help you.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your lungs get constricted, or collapse, or something, you're done.
[SPEAKER_02]: If something just blocks, blocks these tubes, you're done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your great volition of this, like that, it's all secondary to it, and that's what you want to see.
[SPEAKER_02]: It extends.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, you do mindfulness rightly, full dispassion, full recognition of death, the nature of death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, urgency is automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the full extent of your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And still being secondary to the fact that you depend upon that which is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you see your control as not being in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I do, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the one.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the Buddha gave that as an alternative to a suit by maraṇasati and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: My, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose the understanding of this also is like, you know, a city, a marana in a city.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you just try and do it off the bat, you still have all the other assumptions and, you know, all the things, like, for example, of, like, assuming material in my thoughts or whatever kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, that's why, I think, you have to come first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, well, no, that's what we assumed in this talk, now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can do anything wrongly, anyway.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, yeah, you need to have the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if you do it like this, it will lead to the result of full dispersion.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't lead you in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, if you do maraṇasati correctly, yeah, it will lead you to arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't do it correctly, it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: In samadhanasati, sotā, basically, it's also the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you get more and more seeing the general level of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what way?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you... First, you just see, like, breathing in and breathing out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, see the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, see the formation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, see all the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You, you, as I said before, you can't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't mean you have to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every next breath, do it differently.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just be breathing, as long as you're breathing mindfully.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a matter of choice, so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is to maintain the mindfulness of that principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like going far with some repetition or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're used to the feeling, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're used to the mind, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: As long as the mindfulness is sort of slipping, or you're getting whatever, or you don't have enough same sharpness, or you're not maintaining the same vision of dispassion and your life depending upon external circumstances, right there, simultaneously present with
[SPEAKER_02]: You're controlling your breath and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Controlling in the sense of intentional, evolutionary, breathing in and out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, yeah, then you keep keeping... that's what I said, you keep it active.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you don't change it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just introduce more to engage you more, to keep you mindful more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the sutra continues all the way to the dispassion and revulsion and nirodha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Almost feels slightly like a stages and then you get down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is presented like the stages, as I said.
[SPEAKER_02]: The casinos are presented as stages, but they're not stages in that manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, how far you can take it, and that's what it results to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't have to take it that far.
[SPEAKER_02]: As they say, like, the first jhāna is sufficient for arhantship, because that's already the principle of the establishment of the mind, rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you can go all the four.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in this is the same, but that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: The four foundations of mindfulness gets fully developed in the one who does the ānāpānasati rightly, and then the dispassion, and this enchantment is the result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we're just more like up to a personal inclination?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can be also choice to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is choice, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, if you're saying you get tired or start to talk,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you need something more particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just for breathing in generally.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Breathe in thinking of your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Breathe in looking at your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, get more involved in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or just breathe in and breathe out if you're mindful enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, mindful enough in regard to the principle of your life depending upon that which is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're breathing there and then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in theory, not in abstraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right there, while I'm breathing in, while I'm breathing out, start discerning that
[SPEAKER_02]: External direction, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't see that domain upon which your life depends, because there will only be a form of accessing that domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just have a recognition that this very act of breathing that is keeping you alive and your body functioning and everything else, is basically liable to things that are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, your life is liable to things that are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, your life cannot be in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you having a passion and desire towards anything,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's dependent upon their life, your senses, your sensuality, sense desires, satisfaction, pleasures, cannot possibly occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one of the general things people with this in their practice still do is, eh... they feel like the meditation is successful, or anvasādhi is successful when it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if it's unpleasant, they're doing something wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I find that the instruction for suggestion is, find breathe in experiencing rapture.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that feeling section.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of... having that feeling, you feel good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you if you look at the other things, then you might be jumping off the cliffs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they did.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentionally look at the... because it doesn't matter, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still the nature of the feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentionally keep your body calm, focus on the rapture and stuff, while you're maintaining the principle of death and your life not being in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because otherwise, you might sort of
[SPEAKER_02]: Make the mind decide, oh, I've had enough of this, and then monks do things that they've done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was like, I don't know, experiencing rapture, and now I'm just, did you go into it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now I'm getting somewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pleasure is not any measure whatsoever of your progress.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically that kind of inshakable
[SPEAKER_02]: unshakable nature of the composure in the peace, in the face of death, which is not pleasant, but that displeasure cannot overwhelm your mind, and that's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're just looking out to some sort of rapture, rapture and excitement or something, well, you're looking in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you're certainly using dhamma for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you should look at the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplating phenomenon, things like... permanence...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if they use anicca there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that was used in satipaṭṭhāna, and it does say that the satipaṭṭhāna will be brought to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_02]: You look at the quality of anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplating cessation or decrease-ation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what the rest is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Decreasing or intensifying.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rising and falling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ceasingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's emotion in the operation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Emotion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there are many more suttas when it says how you experience relinquishing and detachment or dispassion and revulsion.
[SPEAKER_02]: By seeing that it's horrible, it's perilous, it's dangerous, it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the mind pulls away from it, turns away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a man being carried to a pit full of burning embers.
[SPEAKER_02]: His mind would be in every other direction except towards burning embers.
[SPEAKER_02]: He'd want to be everywhere else except there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what ānāpānasati provides you with, if done rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is, it is the very core of your experience, so to speak, even spatially speaking, like the breathing, the center of your body, the center of your... well, so it appears, the center of your point of view, the center of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, you uproot it from right there, and then you... there's nothing you can take as yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you've kind of given up the ownership of your breath...
[SPEAKER_02]: Through seeing it's determined by...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through seeing that your control, your intention, is only fairly relative and given, which means it's not fundamentally your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're basically, yeah, putting things in the right order, mindlessly putting things in the right order, seeing where the breath, your control, is rooted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you see that whatever
[SPEAKER_02]: Else is here, ambiguous, and general, and not clear, and vague.
[SPEAKER_02]: It shares the same nature as everything of these things that I've understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to chase your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: It gets kind of... it gets affected by it, by that kind of blanket application of that principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: I gave an example before, like antibiotics.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't necessarily know
[SPEAKER_02]: Which bacteria is sort of causing the problem, by taking the general one, you know, well, whatever it was, it was also affected by this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's only possible when you have the right principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the right view has to come first.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just be doing mindless agreeing and expecting.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you should be trying anyway.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're a guru, you should be trying to understand things, to understand the nature of satipaṭṭhāna, understand the nature of feelings, the nature of suffering, the nature of freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't fool yourself about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot do it rightly if you know what the right way is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hear that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I perceive it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a degree of trial and error.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to keep... That's why, again, as I said, the closest comes to some sort of method is constant striving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Relentless.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even when you're resting, don't give up the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's, eh, anyway, turning us, seeing the structure, looking at all those things, creating that, where everything's rooted, pushing us, trying to... Well, it's just, it's annihilating us.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_02]: The center.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, the center phase is long gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the notion of center cannot even be conceived anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: The notion of I am the center.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, like, Sotāpanna cannot think like Putujan anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can remember how it was, but you can't think, like... You just can't think that the center is over there.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no, no, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, in order for you to center something, means you need to have... well, you need to have the space around it to put it in a center.
[SPEAKER_02]: But its whole direction is out of your control, and you can't even access it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever the center might be, it's it's on the other side.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means it's not really a center, because they will only require the assumption of certain space, and this precedes that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then it's just centerless, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: selfless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, that's where you get your, uh, idea, I think it's, you know, what I was saying in France.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, I'll never find you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll never be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically,
[SPEAKER_02]: The front, behind, up and down, before or after, all of that is already secondary to that because of which your life is there determined as it is, to that upon which your life depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even you have a notion of my life depends upon something, that's already within that upon which your life depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, any spatial direction, any time application of thought is already within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there is no outside of it that you can possibly conceive.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all you can do is experience dispassion towards it, because you know that it's liable to things that are not in your control, because of which this, which is already in control, is in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really in your control, because if it were, you would be controlling its fate as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same principle, like, the body is liable to sickness, thus it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, anybody, everyone understands that thought, in a way, to a degree.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's... if you're really to understand that thought, you will fully let go of sensuality, become anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just taken to a different extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, take that thought and pair it with the relentless drilling and not resting, and, yeah, you'll be free from sensuality, even as a kutujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's highly unlikely you'll remain kutujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you have plenty of dharma instruction around you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's the same principle that you apply to the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: The notion of space, the notion of time, the notion of thoughts, intentions, again, rooted, or rather depend upon that which you cannot even conceive or think of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that, sādhyos, you basically, you...
[SPEAKER_02]: You still use it, but you have renounced, extinguished any notions of ownership in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, you extinguish any notion of ownership in regard to the body, and what the body provides.
[SPEAKER_01]: We were saying the other night, like, I was in a car, and I like doing that in the car, car meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eyes closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just feeling the other car moving past, or moving, and
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the mind doesn't want to think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's it's it's threatening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is still
[SPEAKER_02]: So, maybe...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, like, when you see that possibility, and you see right here, in front here,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I get an answer, it's been detached.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see, in a mindful manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, mindfulness is the only... Then it's just... there is an experience, in the sense of, yeah, a very dangerous, perilous, close to death experience, but even that, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I guess.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you stick to that, even when you're not just in the car, you would be basically practicing this passion correctly, which means, sooner or later, it will take root more and more.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it becomes self-apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, when you go back to the breath, you know, I was saying, probably it's crucial, actually, when doing an ānāpānasati, if you're in a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, actually, it feels kind of... first, actually, you can develop mindfulness, and it's not so much like, I feel such a pleasant feeling, but this feeling of mindfulness becomes like an unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, the feeling is present, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, when you were talking about, like, the dying process,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, even the mind, even the thought itself becomes unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, like, the dying man has only wisdom to rely upon, if he has developed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he hasn't,
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be in ultimate despair, which is why death is so hard and difficult as an experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: But wisdom, not being dependent upon any phenomena based upon six senses, but it's in regard to the six senses, the five senses and the mind, that's what stays.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the peace is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the equilibrium is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where non-fear, lack of fear is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where Anuj is, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was also thinking, like, sometimes we're talking about peaceful death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually probably the rule is, like, the death has to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the only peaceful death is arahant's death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no such thing as a peaceful death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless one is an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people were saying to Ādhārācārya about how to prepare people to have a peaceful death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ādhārācārya was saying, if I remember correctly, he also saw the pigs just about to be slaughtered with a smile on their face.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they just... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, that's not good.
[SPEAKER_01]: To me, it's a peaceful moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something a little bit different, eh... in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the thing is, yeah, I mean, maybe it means for something more, but Tom has a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's probably going to have to qualify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, there are some things that are more peculiar, feelings, more tone of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it can... you can designate it like that for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not saying that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just saying that, as a general designation, you will have to qualify much more and probably to mislead more people.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't mean that, for you, it doesn't stand closer to that which feeling is, than if you use designation feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Call it whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind being shaped of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, sure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The general, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means that's what the mind is at the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have... step outside the mind and see the mind in such... like, oh, my mind is such-and-such shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in a surrounding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you find the mind in a certain shape, in a certain mood, in a certain sort of... Yeah, I'm not taking external view and saying this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can describe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what Satipaṭṭhāna does.
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows his mind as expanded mind, as shrunken, as depressed mind, as elated mind, as light mind, as heavy mind, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can use very general designations, because you can't have more particular ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I'm saying I'm paying attention to the breath, I intend to breathe, and I'm looking directly at that as much as I can, just, you know, well, focus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just everything, what arises, arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripheral, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: And seeing that as though that peripheral is the foundation, the nutriments, the intention to breathe calmly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get it now?
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, whatever arises...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what am I looking for?
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, I look for the shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means the shape of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm looking at my intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you discern the shape as a given.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, on a more practical, and probably a bit more useful, for wider audience, I guess, would be not getting, like, too abstract about this shape or that shape, but just discerning the shape, or rather discerning the mind affected by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, discerning the mind not affected by sensuality, discerning the mind affected by the will, discerning the mind not affected by the will, discerning the mind affected by delusion, by non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... that's kind of very fundamental.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning the mind affected with pleasure, affected with displeasure,
[SPEAKER_02]: Because none of those shapes of the mind, expanded or this or that, are kind of impersonal, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're all being felt, either pleasantly or unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But whether it's the pleasure caused by the peace, freedom, or it's the pleasure caused by the prospect of sensuality, elation, delight, which means, let's say, self-pleasure, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you want to see that, because, like, you might not be, you might not be
[SPEAKER_02]: Engaging in any sensual acts, you may be well restrained, but the mind is still affected by the possibility of sensual pleasure that you are welcoming.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to be stop... you want to stop the welcoming, you want to undermine the possibility of pleasure affecting you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't undermine the possibility of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't undermine
[SPEAKER_02]: Eyes seeing things they will find... that they will find agreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ears hearing sounds that they will find agreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you have eyes, ears and other senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what you can do, is on the level of that mind, free your mind from the welcoming and delighting and the possibility of being so.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, whatever is particularly, you can't give in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because possibilities are more general, more fundamental, than the particular arising of any of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if your mind is free from possibility,
[SPEAKER_02]: of delighting in pleasure, cannot actually delight in any pleasure, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it's a discussion that regards to... That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The practice of loving-kindness, for example, the Mettā, is saying, basically, you have, eh... surmounted the possibility of your mind giving in to ill-will, welcoming ill-will, taking joy in ill-will, engaging in ill-will,
[SPEAKER_02]: You have removed that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, automatically, you're experiencing matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Indirectly, you're experiencing matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not forcing anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there, you focus your attention on your breathing or whatever, and when you see the peripheral sort of experience as a whole, the notion of the mind there, see, is that liable to sensuality?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you have a sensual thought now, will it cause a delight and excitement?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to remove that on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by not delighting in it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't remove the actual possibility, but you can remove your delight in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you stop delighting in the possibilities of sensuality, you cannot possibly engage in it, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just... You start talking about the mind and the shape of it, and I'm just telling you, rather than...
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a risk of getting lost in abstract, if you start sort of drawing lines and shapes and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, for some people, it might work in the same manner, but the point is dispassion.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is non-centrality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're thinking about the shapes of your mind, it should lead to dispassion.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's not, you're not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just do discussion, say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just say no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you could, theoretically, if you say no on the right peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripheral, if you say no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just if you say no, actually, and then hope that everything else will be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah, when he's talking about peripherals, proper mindfulness...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...is happening, so... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not getting involved, though.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm getting... No, peripherally seeing it and peripherally renouncing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: mindfully seeing it and mindfully renouncing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: The distance, the weather in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it still liable to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you are responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not responsible for eyes finding certain things agreeable, certain things disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you are responsible
[SPEAKER_02]: for maintaining the notions of delight and assumptions in your mind, which then keep the mind susceptible and liable to changes of weather, changes of mood, of sexuality, of ill will, of delusion, of complacency.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a new one.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when the mind is bright and mindful, you look at the nature of that and then try to sort of spread, so to speak, on that peripheral level, that nature, further and further and further, until
[SPEAKER_02]: You can understand how it can become impenetrable to the possibility of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot prevent possibility of sensuality arising and manifesting itself, but you can certainly train your mind to turn away from it, to stop delighting in it, stop welcoming it, stop assuming it as good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibility, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Before the actual engagement.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, not perhaps first in the sense of first, second, but simultaneously present with the actual engagement, what you preceded.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more general, it's more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_02]: Close that door.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there's not a lot of delighting in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, nothing specific, nothing specific.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just the possibility of enjoying pleasure based upon body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't enjoy pleasure, don't go there.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about going there or not going there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That thing has already arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just, like, stop welcoming that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop regarding it as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop finding it agreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop not seeing it as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not seeing it as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Automatically, you're welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I don't see it as dangerous, you might not welcome it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not more than that man will go out from the pit till burning embers.
[SPEAKER_02]: And often in this way, the danger became apparent, and the mind was liberated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the danger is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not contriving, you're not fabricating any danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might have to do so initially, so that it can kind of correspond to the actual danger that can then be discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is actually dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Life-threatening dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just a sensual thought, let alone sensual action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's, eh... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... perhaps such a good story, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You got to give reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, all that is accurate, but all that is on the level of reasoning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means all that is not directly seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see the dangerous danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you can reason all you want, out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, think about the phenomenon of danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: How, like, if there is a danger to your life now, right here, how would you feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you should feel when the sensual thought arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like your life is on the line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sensual thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not any thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not any agreeable thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just a thought pertaining to the pleasure based upon body.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to become neurotic about it either, in the sense of, like, nothing agreeable I must accept.
[SPEAKER_02]: And everything is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are wholesome things out there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, if the mind is not thinking, not thinking any sensual things, and is at the same time withdrawing itself from being sort of liable to the touch or the possibility of the sensual things, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it cannot be touched by the possibilities either, even if they are arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even on the level of mind, a thought of pleasure doesn't pull the mind towards that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to keep pressing it further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keep it there.
[SPEAKER_02]: This turn was there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Set it there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's actually first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when I say the surmounting, the possibilities of sensual pleasure, that's what the suttas, when they talk about preventing the unarisen, unwholesome states from arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: You prevent them by not delighting in the possibility of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, un-arisen, unwholesome states are the possibilities of the sensuality, which is unwholesome, are the possibilities of unwholesome, be it sensuality or will.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, un-arisen, unwholesome equals possibility of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where you basically, on that level, you free your mind from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if the mind is free on the level of the un-arisen states,
[SPEAKER_02]: of the unwholesome nature, then the mind cannot be controlled, touched, or engaged with the states that are actual, right in front of you, arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: The maintenance of wholesome states, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, it's again, it's in regards to the unarisen wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: Possibility of the wholesome states, that's what you train in regard to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you maintain the actual arisen wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's seen a danger, seeing the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Please say gratification.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, seeing the danger in being liable to the arising of the unwholesome states, of unwholesome nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the danger in the possibility of unwholesome affecting you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You see the gratification in the... Sure, in the unwholesome world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, would you be delighting in the possibility of unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Delighting?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, not in a sensual manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to welcome and... Well, not delighting, it's the also... Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might want it, but that wanting will be on the level of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, wanting, recognizing, this is liberation, this is the freedom, this is the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Chanda.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can go both ways.